so uh for those who are joining uh i am
laura dubrey the co-chair of this
webinar uh we have two more minutes
before we formally start
we
will be
officially starting at 11.03
[Music]
ah there's lauren and alan
that's not laying here yet
i forgot about elaine
yes he's there i see him he's online
okay good
yeah we're up to 80 participants
dr dagger it's uh good to see you
seen you in a while yes same here
we all meet in cyber space those days
okay thirties uh we will be starting uh
just now i think uh it's close to 1103
good morning everyone welcome
to this
webinar that is part of the precision
convergence capacity building webinar
series
this series is co-hosted by miguel
center for the convergence of health and
economics and
the pittsburgh super computing
center
the series was
started about a year ago
in the
following up the hpc high performing
um computer
19 consortium that had been
engaging
psc and other
[Music]
research computing institutions around
the country with ibm and many of the
other
data
business uh for
accelerating our ability to bring
solution to covet 19. this consortium
was created for
seeing to what extent we can bridge the
omics and all the digital capacity to
accelerate
solution to covet 19
profiling uh characterizing of the virus
vaccine and so on and so forth and
we said
uh what if we were to take as a silver
lining of the kobe
19 continue building of this capacity
of ai and digital
technology and others to see to what
extent
we can bridge the various
science uh that are needed if we are to
bring
uh in a timely manner a solution to real
world problem whether it is pandemics or
whether it is climate change and so on a
lot of it is tied to the fact that in
the last 250 years
we have changed a lot the context within
which the human machine has evolved
the first industrial revolution was uh
it is 250 years ago
it's essentially a few seconds in the
journey of mankind so this series is
really to bring
the
scientists the action leader
that are operating on multiple scale in
saying can we go beyond than what we are
each doing so far so before
i introduce uh
more
what is it we'll do together during this
uh next two hours and the keynote
um i
uh would like to ask my co-chair to
introduce himself
and then i will come back for
introducing
uh
the keynote go ahead sean
hi my name's uh sean brown i'm the
director of the pittsburgh super
computing center a joint computational
research center between carnegie mellon
university and the university of
pittsburgh and i'm also the vice
chancellor for research computing at the
university of pittsburgh i'm very
excited about
our talk today and our panel follow-up
panel discussion so i will take less i
will not take any more time so thank you
all for joining us
thank you sean uh very briefly in a
nutshell the way we spend the next two
hours
um i have been for those of you who were
the on the series before we always start
by saying it's not a webinar it's a
capacity building webinar where we
convene a keynote of significance uh in
advancing
science uh in
one of the three domain the human
machine the man-made system or the
computer
and we build a panel where everyone is
carefully selected to
not only be
aware and complementary to the keynote
but each of the panelists as you can see
are also bringing those uh the their own
perspective in advancing this precision
uh convergence program uh so we have the
first uh 30-40 minutes of the keynote
presentation
and then
we have a first round
of panel where each of the paralysis
bringing
a three to five minutes commentary from
their perspective in response to the
keynote presentation but also from their
own
uh their own uh knowledge and so on um
the keynote has about two or three
minutes for each of them to
answer in the first round uh and then uh
in the second part then
if there are questions uh from the
audience sean will be managing them from
uh the chat room uh to address them
after the first round of the panelists
and then
we have a second round where everyone
including the kingdom
uh is invited uh to kind of
do the one minute commentary
of where can we go as a world community
if we are to
really reach a scale uh into the
transformation that we are all
wanting to achieve okay
uh so uh this is um uh
this is kind of the logistic aspects uh
i would like before introducing uh dr
carl christian to position a bit his
presentation within the continuum
of
the webinar we have been
having
over the last year
on the psychology south side we have
been having as kino roy bom mister
um daniel uh schachter uh the last one
on which
carl was on the panel was by
constantine sediquides all of them uh
really
one can arguably say uh the most
influential
living scientists in the study of
psychology and the mind and the and and
so on um and uh we have been and in the
last webinar where carl was presented
was on the panel
the discussion was to see um to what
extent the cell to what extent the cell
the self and the end the psychology
could be placed on the same platform of
the whole biology when we look at a
human being being
evolving
not only for survival but also for
achievement and this is within that
context that
we
have been uh discussing and that's why
the work of the the work that will be
presented today
on the self evidencing for individual
and collective agency to what extent can
this substantive knowledge of human
uh biology psychology
and real world can be brought together
in some degree of formalism that help
bridging all of the above so that is why
without further
introduction i'm extremely pleased to
um
to welcome carl freestone and as we call
as shawna said
uh we are doing introductions very short
because there is um
there is a limited time with the
richness of the intellectual and human
capital we have together in the next two
hours so
calfistone is a theoretical
neuroscientist and authority on brain
imaging
i won't enumerate the various
statistical
methods that he has been developing uh
his most its main
contribution uh to theoretical
neurobiology is a free energy principle
for action
and
perception which is the focus uh of uh
his style today so carl if you excuse me
i will not give a read the whole uh the
whole
um description of of your achievement
and i will
go with you go to you directly for your
presentation
well thank you very much it's a great
pleasure to be back here and it's now my
turn to do a keynote of significance
i've got to do that with two constraints
first of all
get everything that's important on the
table within half an hour
and also use not my favorite words but
the favorite words of my panelists so
we've all met um last week just to sort
of cover the key themes that we want to
bring out in discussion so my job is to
try and
situate those um within this keynote and
this keynote's um
going to address
the first principle account of sentient
behavior so a story about how i behave
and how we behave that can be elaborated
uh from the first principles of
self-organization and the
um approach i'm going to take is from
the point of view of self-evidencing so
i'm going to introduce the notion of
self-evidencing as simply as possible
motivate why this might be an
interesting approach in relation to
current perspectives on artificial
intelligence machine learning um and
then try to ground it in the
neurobiology as was um you know
my brief or our brief
in the introduction um i'm going to take
a special focus on the mechanics of
belief propagation
and in particular
how we organize our behavior to solicit
the right kind of data that supplies
evidence for our own existence and sell
that notion that imperative as an
important drive for um active engagement
with the world and then finally uh
talking to the collective aspect and the
importance of
collective agency and shared narratives
so
self-evidencing what do i mean by that
and i simply mean that
everything that we think or do
can be understood or described in terms
of trying to maximize
moral evidence so what's moral evidence
it's simply the probability of some
observable outcomes
given my model of how those outcomes
were generated
and on this view we can associate belief
updating with perception where i'm
denoting beliefs here as with cue of
some hidden states or causes latent
states of the world that are generating
these outcomes
and in a similar vein
i also i'm going to assume that we have
beliefs about what we're going to do
about our actions and prior to selecting
a particular action we have to form
beliefs about what is the most likely
action you that i'm going to commit to
and the argument here is that both of
these these kinds of leap updating
are
driven by an imperative to maximize
model evidence
so that has a degree of construct
validity in relation to established
normative accounts of behavior um i've
listed a few here if i read this log
evidence as
the value of an outcome in the sense
that if i prefer
these kinds of outcomes or these
outcomes are characteristic of me
then i should behave to secure those
kinds of outcomes as valuable outcomes
and from that we can spin off uh if i
was in psychology reinforcement learning
i was an engineer
we could cast this as optimal control
theory and indeed if i was an economist
it would just simply be one simple
specification expected utility theory
if on the other hand i was an
information theorist i would read this
quantity or the negative of this
function this negative log probability
of an event or an outcome uh conditioned
upon a model as a self-information
sometimes called surprisal or simply
surprise
and it is this quantity that is uh i'm
going to associate with um attractable
measure of the value or the negative
value or the surprise namely a free
energy and this
quantity
suggests that everything we do is in the
service of minimizing surprise we can
read that as the principle of maximum
mutual information on the max principle
uh principles of minimum redundancy or
maximum efficiency that can be
attributed to horus barlow and indeed
the free energy principle which is a
formalism i'm going to use
um
this is nice because the expected
self-information
expected surprise before an event has
happened
is entropy
so this also says that we perceive and
act in a way to minimize on average
entropy and of course that's the holy
grail things like self-organization and
physics energetics and if i was a
physiologist it would simply be a
statement of homeostasis that i am in
the game of keeping my outcomes within
some viable bounds minimizing their
dispersion or the dissipation i.e their
entropy and if we are a statistician
i would treat this quantity as the model
evidence and from that we can spin off
things like the bayesian brain
hypothesis evidence accumulation and
various implementations of that such as
predictive coding so
i'm going to unpack
this quantity this surprise
in terms of value in terms of a free
energy functional
and try and
give you a number of different
perspectives that um on this quantity so
the first perspective is that
we can regard this statement as a first
principle statement about the
imperatives for self-organization that
inherits directly from james's maximum
entry principle
so in maximizing um this free energy
functional here
we are effectively increasing the
dispersion of our beliefs we're keeping
our options open to the greatest extent
possible under some constraints
and i hope we're going to talk about
constraints later the particular
constraints here are afforded by
something called a generative model that
is usually um decomposed into a
likelihood and a pry the likelihood of
some outcomes given their causes latent
states in the world and some prior
beliefs or preferences about the states
that i am likely to be exposed to in
terms of generating my observable
outcomes
there's another way of writing down this
quantity which provides a complementary
perspective and that's the kind of
perspective you get
if you're a statistician
so a little rearranging the terms in
that free energy functional and to
express it as a mixture of accuracy and
complexity
so the accuracy here is simply the
expected log likelihood outcomes given
my beliefs about how those outcomes were
formed
whilst the complexity is a very
interesting term
in this setting it's just the difference
between my beliefs after
and before
seeing some observations or evidence for
beliefs
about particular states of the world so
it literally scores the degree i change
my mind when i see an outcome or i
observe something it scores the cost of
belief updating
and the story that i'm going to tell
for the remainder of this talk is that
if i have to choose what to do that will
get some more information get some more
observations
then i can cast behavior
of a sentient sword in terms of choosing
those actions that maximize the accuracy
and minimize the complexity i expect
following that action and it turns out
that the expected accuracy complies
exactly with the principles of optimal
days in design while the optimum the
expected complexity turns out to be risk
and is exactly the quantity that
underwrites uh optimal decision theory
optimal bayesian decision theory so what
i'm saying is that
putting these two things together
gives us self-evidencing in the spirit
of um selecting those behaviors or
actions that maximize this expected free
energy and implicitly um increase the
expected
evidence
so just to make this insight more
heuristic and to compare and contrast
with alternative approaches imagine
you're an owl and you're hungry and if i
was there with you
i would be asking somebody on the front
row
what are you going to do
and invariably they give me the correct
answer well i'm going to look for my
food i'm going to search for my prey
and that simple answer tells us
something quite fundamental
about the way that you would write down
a calculus for
sentient behavior um and the two kinds
of calculus i'm going to compare and
contrast and then bring together um
later on um rests upon the notion of a
value function of states of the world
so
i could say okay
if i had some function that scored the
goodness the value of a state that
ensued following at the next time point
following a chosen action u
i could then just choose for every given
state of the world the best or the
the value function maximizing action to
give myself a state action policy
is this kind of calculus
apt for describing
behavior well the answer i'm searching
for my food tells you no it can't be
because searching is an act that reduces
your uncertainty about the location of
your brain but uncertainty is not a
function of states of the world it's a
function of the beliefs about states of
the world and so we have an alternative
way of writing down good behavior and
that is something that maximizes a
functional function of a function in
this instance that function is beliefs
about the states the world that would
ensue if i committed to a particular
action it's a very different kind of
functional form
the other
aspect of searching for food
tells you something also about the
nature of the best way to describe or
the best policies and that's it matters
whether i search my food and eat it or
try to eat it and then search for my
food
that tells one immediately that what
we're um chasing here is a way of
describing a sequence of actions or
actions over time and this functional
then becomes
technically a path integral um a sum of
goodnesses over time and that gives you
a very different functional form for the
optional policy it's now a sequential
policy that maximizes this uh path
integral of an energy functional of the
senior moment it's a free energy
functional
the reason i'm using those words is just
to refer to the two kinds of principles
that we could appeal to
in underwriting these different
approaches to good behavior
so this state action policy is
predicated on belmont's optimality
principle
we'll find that in optimal control
theory dynamic programming deep
reinforcement learning basic decision
theory and so on
this on the other hand
has a slightly deeper and simpler
heritage it's it's basically a
variational principle of station
reaction um the free energy principle
being one instance of that um we will
see later that this is more apt to
describe things like artificial
curiosity or in robotics intrinsic
motivation and is more concerned with
data gathering optimal bayesian design
than not based in decision theory and i
repeat is concerned with optimizing
sequences of policies under uncertainty
using things like partially observed
markov decision processes
so principles of least action um
this is the and i apologize for the the
equations here there's a beautiful
symmetry um between the functional forms
of this
way of writing down evidence in terms of
complexity or accuracy
and
the
things the equivalent things that you
are optimizing
if you are selecting those behaviors
that you think will maximize the
expected free energy
so
just writing down again an expression
for
the free energy here in terms of
accuracy and complexity and rearranging
it in a particular way here that people
in machine learning will recognize so
just switching these terms around
we can also express this as the log of
the evidence the probability of some
outcomes given a model
plus something a kr divergence
something that is never less than zero
because this thing is never less than
zero this quantity this free energy now
becomes an evidence bound uh known by
the acronym and elbow and evidence lower
bound
machine learning
so given these two ways of carving up
this objective function um what would
they look like in expectation well what
happens is that
the expected complexity becomes risk the
expected inaccuracy becomes ambiguity
the expected log evidence on negative
log evidence becomes expected cost and
the expected divergence becomes expected
information gain
and this is beautiful but it's also
quite unremarkable because uh most
people in one field or another already
know about this so for example if we
ignore
um the expected value or the negative
expected cost then we're just left with
this expected divergence what is this
well it's simply the difference between
my beliefs about states of the world
in the future following a particular
policy
if i were able to observe the
consequences of that behavior relative
to if i were not
so it scores the information gain
or the reduction of uncertainty about
hidden states or latent states of the
world afforded by this particular policy
so it's the epistemic affordance of this
policy and the visual search literature
this will be known as expected bayesian
surprise more simply it's just the um
the mutual information or the expected
mutual information conditioned on a
on a policy
um
i'm going to successively remove sources
of uncertainty from the table and just
see what emerges and what's going to
happen is we'll get back to the
development optimality principle and
expected utility theory but on route um
let's assume that we live in a universe
there's no ambiguity states or outcomes
and outcomes and states i can see
everything directly
and this means that we can ignore the
ambiguity term and supplant the s's for
o's and vice versa we're just left with
this which is another
kl divergence and it just scores the
difference between what i anticipate
will happen if i pursue this policy and
what a priori i prefer to happen given i
am me this is the expected the value or
the negative um the negative uh cost um
expresses the probability and so this
minimizing this difference this
divergence between what i anticipate and
what i prefer
is known in engineering as kl control
and economics it's sensitive control
and it's simply a description of
behavior in which you choose those
things to do which minimize the
divergence of the outcomes that you
expect
under a generative model a mixture of
likelihood and prize um
namely your pride preferences and then
finally
if we remove
the kind of uncertainty that is
reducible by my epistemic foraging or
responding to epistemic affordances or
the intrinsic motivation for finding out
what would happen if i did that then we
could ignore the expected information
again we're just left now with the
expected cost and that clearly um can be
read now as expected utility theory if
you're in economics
so in summary
what we're saying is that there's a
simple way of writing down
self-evidencing that speaks to
engagement with the future and the way
that we choose what to do next and we
can decompose
maximization of expected free energy uh
which we refer to as active influence
in terms of two dual aspect bayesian or
dual aspect basing optimality one in
terms of maximizing expected value or
minimizing expected cost uh in accord
with um bayesian decision theory based
on making base optimal decisions and at
the same time
we're maximizing expected information
gain and this
inherits from the work of people like
dennis lindley um
on optimal basic design basically
designing your experiments in a way that
you solicit those data that resolve the
greatest amount of
uncertainty about your hypotheses or
models of how data are generated
um so to close i'm just going to race
through
things you can do with this
first principle like account or method
um
one the first thing that one can do
obviously is to simulate and uh um in
silico reproduces
agents and artifacts and see how they
behave but to do that you have to commit
to a generative model these are the
constraints that
when supplied to james's maximum entropy
principle gives you the free energy
principle so
one key thing is that if you can write
down a generative model
you can always express it in terms of a
probabilistic graphical model
what this slide is meant to convey is
that then there always exists something
called a factor graph so why is this
important well the factor graph is just
if you like a dual or a
an adjunct way of expressing your
genitive model in a way that reveals
immediately the nature of the messages
that need to be passed amongst the
different belief structures that are
over the random variables the hidden
causes um that
generally are organized according to
this markov decision process so that we
have um outcomes that are generated by
states of some universe
those states generate outcomes through a
likelihood mapping
that's a likely part of my genetic model
but the states evolve over time through
transition matrices that constitute my
prior beliefs about the dynamics and the
contingencies and the laws um that
denote the causal structure in my
universe and it is these transitions
that i'm in charge of uh in terms of the
policies that i select and i select my
policies to maximize the expected free
energy here
so that would be a generic graphical
model description of an active
engagement uh with the world and this
would be the equivalent factor graph
that tells me the message passing that i
would need to do to do the brief
updating to realize and integrate this
system to simulate um self-evidencing or
active inference and there are all sorts
of great games you can play here in
terms of once you know
the message passing the uh the belief
the the form the functional forms and
schemes of belief propagation that's in
some way must be under the hood for any
given generative model you want to
commit to and you can start to think
about how this would um
what this would look like in various
systems such as the brain i won't go
into this but there's a again a very
beautiful and very simple mapping
between the time scales of different
updates during say belief updating a
perceptual inference slower updating of
the parameters of my generative model
that we can associate with learning and
the
action selection that ensues from this
notion of planning as inference in terms
of updating beliefs about what i'm going
to do next and we can map
this uh these functions onto different
brain areas and functional brain
architectures and make predictions about
the nature of those architectures which
i'm sure we'll be talking about later we
can simulate behavior i'll whip through
uh one example just to sort of demystify
and just pick out the most important um
aspect of this
of this formulation
which is basically this um this balance
um this dual aspect
optimal bayesian design versus optional
base in decision theory um and show that
in fact that balance is systematically
deterministically specified by how much
i know about my environment effectively
it dissolves the exploration
exploitation uh dilemma um and to
illustrate that there's a little game
that we've created here we're simulating
this mouse and the game
there for this mouse is it has to in
just two moves
secure its reward that could be on the
left or the right of the teammates
and so it could either take a chance and
find out where the reward is it has to
stay in one of the upper arms um if it
chooses one so you know half the time it
may be right and spend two bits moves
with its reward the other half of the
time it will be wrong
and has to stay with the non-rewarded in
the non-rewarded location for its two
moons but it has another choice and this
is the important
choice from the point of view of this
little demo
we've also equipped this universe with
a deontic queue an instructional cue
that if it uses one of its moves to
actually go and see the color of the
queue down here this q tells it where
the reward is so now it can choose to
use the first move to explore
to resolve uncertainty about where the
reward is and then the second move to go
with a degree of confidence to secure
its reward
um now clearly
from an expected utility point of view
these are equally um viable options but
from the point of view of
self-evidencing with this epistemic uh
affordance in play it's going to be much
more attractive for
this little mouse to go and resolve
uncertainty by going straight down to
the uh informative view when you
simulate this mouse under a particular
giant model using those update equations
i showed you a couple of slides ago
that's exactly what happens um so we
start off uh with the
little mouse going down finding where
the reward is and then sitting on its
reward for the final move um but as time
progresses
these details are unimportant the only
thing we're trying to convey here is as
time goes on
what we've done here
is leave the reward always on the
left-hand side
so that
this mouse now accumulates the belief
that reward is always in the same place
and as it gets more and more confident
it accumulates more evidence that the
reward is always in the same place the
epistemic affordance or attractiveness
of the instructional cue starts to weigh
and the epistemic value the epistemic
affordance will at some point become
smaller than the expected utility or the
expected cost um of continuing to forage
epistemically and at which point the
behavior reverts to explorative exposure
behavior where it will go straight to
where it now knows the reward is and
stay there for two minutes and we can
see that occurring after about 20 trials
in this particular example
and
that switch in behavior affords the
opportunity now to do all sorts of
interesting in silico experiments and
make predictions about either
neuronal responses to the chosen versus
unchosen option um
[Music]
or one can
look at the encoding of
behaviors and locations in terms of
place cell activity and indeed we can
simulate this negativity paradigms or
ball paradigms by just comparing
trials
where
at the beginning there was lots of
uncertainty so everything is novel
everything is an audible
with trials with exactly the same
behaviors and sensory stimuli
or sensory outcomes but now after the
mouse has become familiar no more was
bored with its environment so everything
now becomes a standard and again we can
uh reproduce with some marker remarkable
fidelity the timing and the from the
forms of simulated electrophysiological
responses so i'm giving these examples
very very quickly just to show that they
are
both grounded in and to a certain extent
inspired inherit from
the neurobiological implementation of
this
this sort of belief updating scheme so
i'll finish now with a um with an
important nod but it'll be no more than
a nod so what does this
kind of formulation bring to the table
when we're thinking about lots of agents
um acting together uh oh um succumbing
to the same kinds of imperative and one
really interesting sort of thing that
emerges technically from this is that we
move from a world in which we're
trying to think and explain the behavior
of a creature or a particle that's
making inferences about it the states of
the world out there the environment
through um observable things and uh over
which
it has control through active things and
we refer to the these two kinds of
variables as a markov blanket we move
from
a structure where there's a markov
blanket separating the internal states
that do the brief updating um from the
outside world of the supplying sensory
evidence and is
subject to our actions upon which we act
if we now think about two of these
agents putting
together
then in fact the external states
disappear because you become my external
states and i become your external states
so there are no more external states
there's just lots of internal states
my brain states your brain states
mutually trying to infer each other and
to cut a long story short um
the um the
the natural consequence of this in terms
of both of us trying to minimize our
surprise
is that we will learn to make ourselves
more predictable
and we will query each other in a way
that we will resolve uncertainty um
about you are i will resolve uncertainty
about you um
but i can only do that if we have the
same shared generative model um i'm
going to close with an example where we
use
the intrinsic motivation the epistemic
affordance to
compel two agents one of which can see a
scene and the other one can't but they
can talk to each other
and because there's this
epistemic affordance or incentive to
resolve uncertainty one agent knows
because it shares the same language with
the other agent
that
she knows what questions to ask to
resolve uncertainty about the scene that
she cannot see but the other agent can
and it's quite simple just to write down
the generative models and the equivalent
graphical uh factor graphs um for a very
simple world where two people are
basically uh playing well they're
playing 20 questions and one person asks
is is is something true or is something
like that and the person say yes or no
and they will slowly share their beliefs
so in this example um
the um the blue um woman
can see two shapes two blocks there's a
red square below and there's a green
square above this lady the teal lady
cannot but she can ask questions so you
can ask this lady is
there a triangle below the stage says no
there isn't um and then this lady knows
that there is a square
but does not know the color and through
this process of making the right moves
um engaging in policies that resolve the
most uncertainty to by maximizing the
expected free energy
she asked the right question about the
color of the square below and finds out
that it's not green so it has to be red
and then she can drill down on the um
the nature of the upper object until
after about four questions she knows
exactly what the other person is looking
at in fact they can switch roles and uh
the other person can check that the
first person has got the right idea and
so the reason that i i bring that to the
table is
twofold one to emphasize um the
importance of this epistemic foraging
in the context of interpersonal
interactions and um
and the mechanics of exchanging beliefs
and the other thing is
what underwrites this which is the
shared generative model that is
necessary to actually communicate
beliefs
things that
are very necessary if you want to
assimilate
belief updating in a distributed way
that has to go across a markov blanket
in some ensemble or collective um now
what's on the other side of the markov
bank it doesn't always have to be the
same it could actually be a you know a a
an eco niche um
but still there's going to be exchange
of information and querying and when
lifted to the cultural level
then we could actually talk about these
uh this formulation as
a one way of understanding cultural
niche construction and then finally if
we now apply these principles um over
different time scales we can also now
think about sort of optimizing model
evidence through moral selection as a
mathematical image of basin um of
natural selection and evolution um so
with that i will close just for the
final world
to to einstein everything should be as
simple as possible but not simpler with
a not this important notion of
complexity um that is an important part
of model evidence so with that
uh i just want to thank those people
whose ideas i've been talking about of
course thank you for your attention
thank you very much indeed thank you
very much carl for this brilliant uh
presentation that get as simple as this
can be
in presenting that complexity
and i really also appreciate that you
squeeze our webinar series into your
busy schedule after
uh the one we have with uh
uh with uh constantine i'd like to
ask uh a twin question uh before
we get to the panel uh uh and that
question is trying to my
i could say
uh let's say sophisticated lay woman or
even just lay woman on understanding
that i think i'm getting to get to of
your
mark uh marco
that is kind of a core aspect which i
believe is um kind of the statistic
statistical space that
that combine or differentiate what is in
an out system if i understand correctly
my two
questions are the following as you most
likely don't know i was throwing 30
years ago at colonel at the time that
behavioral economics was starting with
the um
with uh zversky kahneman and uh dick
taylor that was very
uh descriptive uh uh vision of the
non-rational side of human behavior uh
in moving toward precision convergence i
progressively
get much more around along the work of
herb simon that is defining essentially
bonded rationality as being resource
rational
within the context of your system so my
first question is to i'm intrigued to
hear you
um
connect your work
with herb simon's view of bundled
rationality and his approach and within
that context also
on the panel
that we were having on
on
when consulting was presenting
is homeostatic view of self-promotion
and there was this debate
between
this model whether the psychological
self-promotion promotion
and the
the biological
protection for immunity and no one was
trying to seize their cause a common
causal mechanism so i would be intrigued
in my question my second question if you
could briefly comment on advancing the
discussion we were having between the
psychological the mind and the self and
then the whole biological business
within the context and the challenge is
answering this in three minutes go
i'll spend the first two on the first
questions excellent questions service
yeah
simon's unbounded rationality i love
that because of course
um there's a nice semantic clash with an
evidence bound so if you go to machine
learning and ask how does a variation
auto encoder work it optimizes its
weights with respect to this elbow so
it's your it's all in the bound so
bounded rationality approximate bayesian
inference defined operationally as
optimizing a variation free energy
literally is is bounded uh optimality
and the the other thing that's nice
about it
is this notion of constraints uh and i'm
using that in the in the sort of json
sense but of course an important
constraint is the uncertainty under
which you're operating so you know
that's why i was so keen to emphasize
that you can tease apart the overall
objective function um
into two bits but remember one bit is
contextualized by the others so the base
optimal rational decision making the
under the um
the the expected utilitarian is always
contextualized by a degree of
uncertainty so there's a value of
information that provides if you like a
a space or a constraint or a context for
and that and you're i'm i'm reading that
in the spirit of bounded rationality
where this is a computational resource
or an information resource and with
respect to the homeostasis yeah i mean i
love constantine's stuff because you
know it it's just lifting this basic
imperative for a generalized homeostasis
a generalized synchrony with your
environment
from the physiology to the self-modeling
to the things that underwrite our
behavior
and speak to this really important
notion that
if it is the case that we behave
in order to secure or realize our the
kinds of outcomes that we prefer
then just to be base optimal in this
generalized sense
is basically to have that sampling bias
and just to
to be to be intrinsically biased and if
you weren't you wouldn't exist you know
if you bring about the things that you a
priori expect and then
that is a sufficient explanation for why
you conserve yourself over time and of
course that's just a statement of
homostasis
thank you so much and so i would like to
ask the panelists to all uh open their
video shifting to sean my co-chair who
can ask his privileged question also and
start uh the panel go ahead sean no i'm
not i'm not going to take that privilege
because i'd like to hear what our
panelists i'm very interested what our
panelists have to say so we'll go ahead
and get it kicked off with our first
round of commentary i'd like to
introduce mark bailey who is the vice
president for re uh vice president for
research at cfar and a professor in the
department of computer the departments
of computer science statistics and
actual science electrical and computer
engineering mathematics epidemiology and
biostatistics and biology at western
university so welcome mark and looking
forward to your commentary
thanks sean and uh thank you thank you
carl for an absolutely beautiful
presentation so you asked in your
opening slide is there some information
theoretic imperative that renders
inference and decision making two sides
of the same coin
and then you've given us this
elegant and and complex model of how
precisely that that might be implemented
and uh i'm a simple person so i needed a
simpler questions i i i said i'm going
to step back
and ask
how might such a mechanism arise
why might we end up in this place
and i suspect most of us here in the
audience have had the experience of
you're using your laptop and it's doing
a computation or a program's crashing
and suddenly it gets very hot
and you know what why is that why is
your laptop getting hot when it's
working harder it's not making toast
it's just moving bits around
and so there's a fundamental disconnect
because we still tend to think of the
physical world in terms of mass and
energy
but you know since the time of john
archibald wheeler we know it's actually
mass energy and information so
information is a fundamental uh
fundamental
core object in our physical universe
and so
wheeler had a tagline it from bit
you know from a bit of information we
can create something physical and in
fact that bit of information is
something physical and then in the 1960s
rolf landauer at
ibm watson labs
conjectured
that erasing information is
thermodynamically dissipative so if you
take a bit of information and you erase
it you clear that bit that will release
energy
this is controversial at the time
there's literature both supporting it
and not sporting it but there's been a
spate of experimental results recently
over say the past two decades that have
really strongly confirmed that yes
erasing of information is dissipative so
information processing and
thermodynamics are linked
so if you if you take this framework and
what we know in theoretical computer
science i'm going to say something is
not quite true so forgive me
the harder the computation
the more deletion is involved in that
computation and the more energy you need
we could spend hours talking about what
i mean by hard what i mean by needing
deletion but just trust me on this one
for now
so the question i come back to is
would evolution select against unbounded
computational complexity which is to say
unbounded energy requirements and i
think that that that's reasonable to say
it would be parsimonious for for
evolution to not prefer systems that
require unbounded amounts of energy and
so this question has been asked in the
literature uh martin novak who is a
famous evolutionary game theorist has a
nice publication in pnas about 10 years
ago on the computational complexity of
evolutionary dynamics and more recently
and on topic for for today uh kaznichiv
at oxford has a beautiful paper in
genetics
with title computational complexity as
the ultimate constraint
on evolution
love it
definitely worth reading so back to the
brain
and to the presentation we the keynote
we've just had
the brain is touring complete of course
any computable function i can compute
with my brain give me a pen and a and
this big enough stack of paper i can
simulate a turing machine but the real
question is
during my my everyday life
whether i'm a mouse in a maze or or me
giving a response to a keynote here
do i spend most of my time in that
regime of super linear recruits
recursively enumerable functions
so am i really doing hard computations
most of the time
and and the answer is i'm not right
we've all had that experience of driving
on autopilot
and there there you know there's a lot
of systems that are working with very
little energy there's there's not a lot
of uh of of hard computation going on
and so what if
the strongest constraint as kennedy
chiefs suggests
on the evolution of brains
is computational complexity
where does that get us well
to push it i'm going to take an extreme
absurd position
what if what psychologists call
attention
what if carl's sentient calculus i love
that term by the way
what if consciousness what we perceive
as consciousness are actually primarily
mechanisms for controlling complexity
there are mechanisms for controlling
computational complexity and everything
else all of the richness i experience in
my conscious life is a happy side effect
of that imperative
that is selected for uh through
evolution and you know i think those are
actually pretty good mechanisms
attention is a great mechanism for for
controlling computational complexity of
course that you know
that was an absurd position to to
propose but i i did it to
invite conversation
in reality there's going to need to be a
balance between this need to keep
computational complexity
low while also providing a robust
behavioral repertoire because you do
exist in an environment and you must
behave in that environment so
computational complexity is not the only
only item on which evolution is
performing selection but i think it's an
important one i think the role of
thermodynamic complexity of neural
computation has been understudied and i
i can't prove this but i'm going to
think about it harder i think if you
pull on this thread you end up with a
model that looks very similar to to what
carl has just presented here
thanks john
thanks yeah carl do you have a response
just maybe a
minute uh response i believe
i'd like to respond for about half an
hour so many great points there okay in
one minute um
right first of all
selection your natural selection the
evolutionary pressure attention
selection all one theme i agree entirely
it's complex i mean it's only half the
story because you've got the accuracy
but under under constraints that the
accuracy about the same it's all about
the complexity so you know
you can see that in statistics through
bayesian model selection um that you're
trying to get the simplest architectures
that will generalize so you don't want
to over parameterize so even the
pragmatic agenda of evolution machine
learning is driven by getting the
simplest explanation explanation
possible so you know there are all sorts
of ways in which one could celebrate
that you know i'd like to talk about
commonwealth complexity and uh universal
computation
janinsky equality is you know so many
right things have been said there but
i've only got one minute so i'll shut up
thank you
i mean to stifle you i just we have a
lot of other perspectives to get to
so i'll turn back over laura
yes and i'm very pleased to uh introduce
conrad
conrad i apologize in advance for my
awful french accent according i
discovered conrad's uh work uh in a
paper on
foraging with the idea of looking at
dopamine mechanism that are finding
where to go and then where to have to
have your your your choice
uh so that extra i'm extremely pleased
to have him uh with us with his lifetime
work on sensory matter
and various aspects of normative model
in
beijing statistic and other he is a
german neuroscientist and professor
at the university of pennsylvania so i
will keep it here conrad to leave you
more time go ahead
three to five minutes i know you have a
lot to say
go ahead
you bet so so let's zoom out just a
little bit now like there's a broader
endeavor in our field which is called
normative modeling
it is
it is used in important parts of
neuroscience it's also the basis of
machine learning arguably what we do in
that field is we say let's try and
derive the optimal solution to an
existing problem
it usually works like that where we look
at the world at the problem maybe that
the brain is solving or at the problem
that we want to solve as
as machine learners
and we write down what our goals are
it's usually like a cost function this
is what we want to optimize not like get
it to be precise most of the time
whatever your definition is
then we will usually have a set of
constraints those things that we cannot
deviate from so mark had a great example
compute is one of them there's many of
many others of them and then there's
prior knowledge that we have about the
world aspects of the world i think carl
carl related to pomdp's earlier and then
what we do is we
take this problem statement and we kind
of derive the optimal solution and if
we're a neuroscientist we compare
behavior maybe to that or we look for
representations in the brain if we're
machine learning people we basically
just see how good we are at solving the
technical problem that we want to solve
so in that sense i think we are all
sitting in the same boat now
where i think there's a rather large
disconnect between the way the keynote
was thinking about it and the way i
think about that field is for me
most of what happens is in the details
of that interface so when i say goal
it's not that simple get it right it's
more like on which data set will we get
it i want to get it right under which
circumstances what will be the future
task that we will have to solve with
that
and same thing with constraints it's not
just like you only have x computations
it's complex
all but the world not like it's not just
a palm dp world it's a world with
structure and causality and like all the
different pieces
so from my perspective all the
interesting things kind of live within
these components that we put into that
so for example if we want to talk about
about curiosity you can say well what
are we curious about well we curious
about causal things because we believe
that in this specific world in which we
are
causal things will generalize to future
props we will talk about which things
are relevant for us but i'm not
interested in information generally i'm
just interested in the kind of
information with which i can give a
great talk
so so so basically for in and and
curiosity within machine learning which
is a huge field with like hundreds of
thousands people of people working on is
all built based on different people
making different assumptions at that
interface now here comes kind of like my
difficulty at some level with the
keynote now like at some level we've
seen an ancestor talk about anzac solo
achieve now the answers isn't different
to like how anyone in machine learning
uses it this we can write the same
problem in a few different ways for
example it's been known since the 60s
that we can convert optimal control
problems into equivalent inference
problems and vice versa
the interesting thing so so that's just
like the same answers just written
slightly differently so
so so from my perspective it's not the
answers per se that is important because
where utility maximizes expected value
for the future
we all agree on the answers what we
don't agree are the pieces what can we
put in what are efficient algorithms and
so forth so at some level the thing that
is missing for me in the approach is
pushing these things at the interface
what are the assumptions about the world
what are the assumptions about their
cost functions what is what exactly can
i say about computation and bits and so
forth
and that then in a way like no in that
talk
dr fresten kind of relates to kind of
any everything that is close to my heart
now let's let's let's let's let's be
positive about that now like curiosity
sentience planning self-evidency shared
narratives it has like all these things
that mean so much to me
but we've only ever seen the answers for
all of them we haven't seen okay how
much does it buy us to make this
assumption versus this assumption so
everything that computer scientists are
concerned with is in a way hidden
because we only ever get to see the
answers and i'm sure that
that there will be at least a minute
maybe more than that of rebuttal to what
i just said
thank you for letting me comment on it
back to you gal
in two minutes
you can take three
that's really generous okay all right
okay i'll split it one and two
so i think i think there are two key
points here um
the first one is you know the status of
naughty theories i think there's a very
general and important point there um
and
for me a normative theory would be you
know being able to write down an
objective function
so
from an engineer's point of view you
know if you can write down the objective
function then the game starts and then
you try and find the best way to satisfy
that under constraints and the the
perspective that the the free energy
principle um that sort of backstories
the active inference implementations it
takes is um slightly different in fact
fundamentally different it takes the
point of view of a physicist and say if
this system exists what is the objective
function so if i was a you know um
a classical physicist i'd be looking for
the lagrangian and what's the way of um
articulating the behavior systems that
um um optimize say their action or their
package global lagrange and well those
are just principles of least action so
it is no mistake that the free energy
principle is sold as a principle of
least action because what is it saying
is that given this system exists
then it must possess this uh lagrangian
that has an interpretation given a
markov blanket as um as a sort of
variational free energy that you'd find
in uh you'd find in um say machine
learning or statistics generally so i
think that's a really interesting
philosophical issue i will leave that
and not say anything else the last
minute will be the second i think
i think pragmatically more important
point that that conway was making he was
talking about getting the details right
getting the the
getting the questions right in terms of
an actual application
of something like the free energy
principle to a particular problem i
think it's absolutely crucial and for me
that really is a distinction between a
generic um
application of the free energy principle
to
what well it's the generative model
that's where all the difficult questions
lie the structure of that genitive model
the complexity
the
ways in which you prune it is it
hierarchical what kind of message
passing scheme is going to be in play
out for this kind of genitive model
continuous visit i've you know so i'm
i'm really acquiescing to to conrad's um
sort of observation and um
that there is something quintessentially
vacuous about the free energy principle
because it is just a method it does not
give you the answer in the sense that
this generative model is fit for purpose
that satisfies exactly mark's complexity
constraints yeah i was just thinking you
know conrad do you talk about some
simplifying make it more efficient uh
which is exactly you know the complexity
part that you would use in say basic
model selection but the point i'm making
here the free energy principle is just a
method it's not a solution the solution
is actually identifying the generative
model that is appropriate for this
situation
you know in this area of study
thank you carl uh sean i think you are
the one to introduce
yeah it's uh my pleasure to introduce uh
dr lauren ross who is an associate
professor in logic and philosophy of
science at uc irvine so we look forward
to your commentary uh lauren
great thank you very much um
this was a
um great talk and it's a pleasure to be
here
i have two questions and the first one
has to do with causation the second one
has to do with constraints
the
first question
is about the type of causality that's
most relevant to this work
in particular the type of causality
that's
present in the generative model itself
um and perhaps also the type that they
suggest
that humans have in mind when their
reasoning or an organism has in mind
when they're reasoning
about the world
um so i'm a philosopher of science and
of course there are
heated debates about
how to understand
causality and the
account of causation
that
is relevant to in particular these
generative models
there are at least two
accounts of causation that are often
discussed in the context of generative
models
one of them are process accounts and the
other are dependence accounts
a process account of causation
is
viewing causation in terms of continuity
typically that there's some kind of
continuity from cause to effect
this is sometimes specified in terms of
a
a spatio-temporally connected process
and in other cases the transmission of
something from cause to effect sometimes
it's referred to as a mark marked
transmission
the
entity that's being transmitted can be
material or it can be energy
there's kind of flexibility with what is
being transmitted the emphasis
in this account of causation is that
there's the transmission of something
and often that there's a kind of
physical connection
through the causal process or from the
cause to the effect
now the second type of
causation is a dependence theory
and
in this framework
causation is understood in terms of
dependency relationships so
effects are
um outcomes or factors that depend on
their causes
and in this sense changes in an effect
depend on changes that you would make
do make or could make to the cause and
you can be completely ignorant of or
indifferent to the transmission of
anything from cause to effect you don't
need that physical connection or you
don't need a transmission of any kind of
material
or perhaps anything else besides causal
influence
the dependency accounts are also related
to control in a number of cases the
sense in which we think causes control
their effects or that causes are a kind
of switch that you could manipulate or
intervene on um and that when you do
that you get control over the over the
effect so the question here is do these
generative models have implications or
suggestions for the account of causation
that
we as humans or that an organism
is using when they're reasoning about
the world um and additionally and
distinctly what type of causality is
involved in the model itself and then
the second question
is
about constraints
i'm very interested in and i very much
like the role of constraints in this
framework
there is um right the mention of
constraints comes up in a number of
places
they are
it sounds like often cited as things
that are limiting a kind of space of
plausible brain architectures that's how
they sometimes come up and they can
include things like real neuroanatomy
maybe anatomical connectivity um
maybe these are empirical constraints
but then the generative model is also
cited as a constraint um so philosophers
of science are very interested in
they've become very interested in
constraints
they
are
interested in clarifying what they are
in particular what role they play and
explanation and understanding
and part of their interest is motivated
by the fact that they seem like a unique
explanatory factor they are not always
causal it seems like maybe in some cases
they are
mathematical or
they involve a kind of law of nature
they're thought to explain limitations
in a possibility space which is
different from how we standardly think
of causes or kind of run-of-the-mill
explanatory factor
so the second question is about
constraints in
your um framework and
in this model if you consider them to be
causal non-causal or if they have some
other character and just for you to say
a bit more about the role that they play
in the model and perhaps also an
explanation and understanding
they're back over you carl for however
much time you want
that's dangerous
i could stick to the three to five
minutes no more
go ahead girl
it's a brilliant question and also
artfully um described to the majority of
us who probably don't know what a
philosophically uh cause and constraint
means but that was very limiting thank
you and so while it's fresh in my mind
the the notion of constraint in this
instance um
i would read that in uh you know with my
physicist hat on um as exactly the way
you described which is a um a way of
describing
disallowed or highly unlikely states of
being in some spa possible space of uh
states of being that just is
um the generative model so
um i've been talking about sort of
active influence and self evidencing
with it with a strong technological
license and uh um
cheek basically um you know
from the physics point of view that
teleology is just not there you're all
you're trying to describe is the uh the
conservation laws or the implications of
certain conservation laws that lead to
uh principles of
usually
symmetry principles like principles of
least action and what that basically
means for describing something
first of all you have to say you know
demarcate the thing from everything else
and that induces markov blanket but once
you've done that then the shape of that
thing and the nature of that thing is
just basically described by
um the sets that uh or the kinds of
states that that thing can occupy in the
things that it can't so the whole thing
is predicated stipulatively on a
constraint specification of thingness
and then that from that you then
interpret
put a teleological interpretation
on that constraint as a generative model
and if you've got a genetic model you've
got model evidence and then you can tell
a story about self-evidencing but in
reality it's you know it's just a you
know a mathematical as a calculus just
to write down the shape of things so the
shape is the constraint and you can
describe that probabilistically in terms
of a generative model it's
literally the probability of causes and
effects
joint distribution over causes and
effects where you're very careful to
specify what you mean by cause and
effect and that's why you need the
markov blanket because you know what's
causing things in me well it has to be
stuff that's not me
so then you have to have a separation so
we you know
i'm just saying uh introducing that um
distinction between cause and effect as
something which is quite a big move that
you've made as a physicist
um because you have to actually write
down how would you discriminate between
a causal effect and you know then you
get into the game of the markov blanket
and the second thing was really
interesting i i would love to hear more
about it
from my perspective and it is a sort of
colloquial and possibly limited
perspective it sounds as if the two
different kinds of causality
are essentially those that are
um
of the kind that a control theorist or
dynamicist or dynamical systems theory
or a physicist would talk about where um
it's not so much important about space
it's so the temporal continuity aspect
that is the if you like the defining
feature of
dynamics um
is
holes causality so as soon as you write
down a launch van equation or a state
space model or a markov decision process
or a hidden markov model anything that
involves time
any mathematical process
that involves time
then you've got causality baked in in
exactly the way that you describe it
either in terms of marked transitions or
transition probability matrices or sort
of um
you know flows um
implicit in state space models or as you
know differential equations all of them
at the end of the day are core causal
structures
um in the um in the control theoretic
sense
simply because
you have described the system of
interest in terms of either discrete or
continuous time equations so you're
talking about dynamics so there is no
other um you know causality um your your
generative model if it's a generative
model of a process that unfolds in time
it is by definition a causal model
inversion of that model basically it
makes inferences you know
of a causal sort selecting the right
model to account for that causal
architecture we'll talk about in terms
of evolution or conrad finding you know
getting the getting the um doing it
under the right kinds of constraints
that is just basically um
using this principle of
least free energy um as a way a method
of getting at that causal architecture
by inverting a causal model which begs
the question what's the other kind of
dependency causality i can certainly see
a sort of a glimpse of a connection with
sort of um pearl like causative static
models but you have to remember that
that kind of do calculus um and that
kind of model that you'd find in things
like structural equation modeling and
your his interventional calculus
that's
um unashamedly about static systems and
unashamedly about usually directed a
psychic grass that don't exist in the in
the you know in the real world
so
um i'm not quite sure about that
dependency status um and of course if
you do use that dependency
sort of causality which we all do when
we report a correlation coefficient as
scientists
i think you're a very shaky ground uh
from the point of view of the physicist
who just deals with the processes that
are not background free because they
have time in them you know if you give a
physicist time uh then you you've also
given him causality so that would be my
take on that uh yeah and but i'm not
sure about those answers it'd be great
to discuss that uh
thank you carl before introducing randy
uh
just a quick comment uh on the uh
on the the the first uh three commentary
i was just finishing uh reading a book
last weekend it's an historical novel uh
from
uh
the touring alan turig and
he
is he was a theoretical mathematician
physician then moved to do whatever uh
he did in his life in his young life and
uh one of his regret that the engineer
had taken over the basic mathematician
in moving forward in understanding
decision making so hearing uh mark
saying that everybody not everybody but
solving the turing puzzle by computer is
uh is doable
hearing you cal saying that uh you
as soon as you have the production
uh a production function you can go
ahead and optimize what i'm asking to
everyone is what if you were being the
same at the same time your heart of
philosopher mathematician and physician
and understanding trying to understand
this real-world behavior in real-world
context so that's kind of my commentary
as we get to the second round of this in
mind and also that commentary allowed me
to introduce a very
uh directly my canadian colleague andy
mcintosh who is the director
of the institute of neuroscience and the
whole technology and the professor at
simon frieza
uh university and very much as a
normal computational neuroscientist very
much moving in that direction of trying
to see how we can bring this precision
convergence randy go ahead
thank you lorette uh hi carl um
this is almost like a phd dissertation
defense i'm thinking
so we have to decide at the end whether
you pass or fail or there's a heavy
revision
um
i'm appreciating the discussion because
i'm getting different perspectives on on
the whole
collective of optimization and objective
functions and generative models
and how we can think about using them
to address different
phenomena and um
what i want to try and
maybe throw out there for for for
discussion
is and this you just mentioned this carl
about time
being
a factor in building these generative
models so let's take into consideration
for instance
different time scales over which which
events that affect us can happen
so there's this event now which is
happening over this the time scale of
seconds
and then our interactions which you you
illustrate at the end of your talk um
there are uh slower time scales that
evolve there are sort of circadian
rhythms we have very you know um
uh
salient events for example we're all
sort of sitting in the middle of this
pandemic which has a scale over several
years probably going to have a cascade
effect that that happens over
subsequent years
so there are social cultural factors
that obviously impact
our own interactions impact our physical
wellness but also our social
dependencies
and um
you know this gets into the notion of
multi-scale models and how to envision
these dependencies in some sort of
generative model which could i guess use
free energy as one of the methods
but i guess the question is whether
you can build in that time scale
interaction where free energy has to
span both within temporal scales but
also between temporal scales
and whether we start getting into this
issue kind of like it's turtles all the
way down then because we're kind of
looking at using exactly the same
objective function
for different types of generative models
but the general model we're talking
about one case is more biological
whereas another case might be more sort
of psychosocial and i'm trying to sort
of reconcile um how to think about these
various time scales in the framework
that we're sort of evolving over the
course of our discussion today
so i'll stop there and we'll uh
let the candidate
reply
don't say this randy sorry
he can't say that because
i don't actually i haven't actually got
my phd yet
ah
seriously i didn't quite go around to it
so so i get one for precision conversion
so that would be quite nice yeah you
have time coral yeah
um
yeah now that excellent question i i can
see you know that that's that question
is also going to come up in the context
of sort of natural selection um you know
later on um so i think a really key
point um and i'm sure you know the
answer that the
so
the importance um of the
the
a commitment to a first principle
account um
is that very much like most of these
principles that the they're fairly scale
free or scale invariant which does not
mean to say the same free energy um
or whatever other function you want to
use
um is optimized at all scales what we're
saying is the functional form the method
you know what it looks like in terms of
you know
what is a function of what and the shape
of those functions that strictly
speaking lagrangian is actually
conserved over different scales
so a lovely example of that in
statistics is the fact that if you're
trying to optimize let's take a um
let's take you know let's take a
variation auto encoder for machine
learning that you know is built to
change its weights to optimize the elbow
the the variational free energy
so it's a canonical state-of-the-art um
21st century free energy um
optimizing machine um but now say i uh
come at this um i've got a choice of
four or uh 400 very short encoders some
of them with six levels some with
different kinds of uh rectilinear you
know
activation functions
you know different kinds of parameters
and i come at this with a model
selection or a selective or sort of you
know using say differential evolution or
a genetic algorithm so what i would then
do is score
the um the quality of each of these
variation auto encoders and then i would
apply a genetic algorithm and do some
sort of your selection i would do
simulated evolution natural selection
the key thing is i'll be using the same
objective function in the sense that i
will be adding together the elbow or
taking the pathogen over the time that
i've the temple scale that i was doing
my selection and that would be known as
basic model selection in statistics so
um the key point here is not the same
quantity that's being optimized in the
moment as i'm inferring or i am learning
and but
by taking the path or you're lifting
that to the next scale it necessarily
has the same functional form and
therefore gives the scale freeness to
the next level of optimization which in
this instance could you know i
i framed as uh bayesian model selection
or structure learning medical
constructivism uh if i was a biologist
this would look like um natural
selection um where i'd now be reading
the free energy as a dump to fitness
just simply self-evidencing maximizing
the likelihood of getting this kind of
phenotype this structure in this eco
niche um you know doing this doing this
kind of um
self-evidencing or um
behavior and so
that
then
formally speaking
what that requires you you really to to
write down is a renormalization group
and practically speaking i think i think
the question has the answer in it that
whatever principle you bring to the
table has to be composable
with the separation of temporal scales
um in the sense that you know i can do i
can be an artifact that optimizes
extremizes my free energy over the next
200 milliseconds and i could do be doing
sort of perception it could be over the
next
week as i learned to ride a bicycle i
could do procedural learning it could be
over the next
three years and i could be doing
neurodevelopment or it could be
transgenerational i would be doing um
i'd be doing natural selection but at
every point
um each of the the objective function
has has if you like a mapping
via the notion of this um scale freeness
and so that the optimization at one
level is essential for the optimization
of the level below and vice versa so if
i was like george ellis i'll be talking
about top down and bottom up causation
now which means i i have to have the
right
heritage as a phenotype in the right
species in order to have the right kind
of brain in order to do the right kind
of learning in order to make the right
kinds of inferences but on the other
hand i need to do the right kinds of
inferences to learn the right things in
order to do the right development so
that so i have the right adaptive
fitness so i can be selected so there's
a circular causality that couples each
of these levels
now your question is can you usually
write that down in silico and start to
actually grow
you know intelligent artifacts or
simulate and model
systems that are subject to these mutual
constraints in the circular causality
that's a really difficult problem and
particularly when any one level
starts to show things like curiosity and
the like you know the
computational complexity is is
has to be met but it is great this is a
challenge and then we come back to
complexity minimization keeping things
as simple as possible right
thanks carl
great and before i introduce our next uh
panelist i want to remind all the
committee members to return your form
about the dissertation so that we can
turn that into the administration
it's my pleasure to introduce dr martin
paulus uh who is the scientific director
and president of the laureate in
institute for brain research in tulsa
oklahoma so uh look forward to your
commentary martin
thanks sean and uh thanks carl um
it um and i i've ever really actually
quite enjoyed the
discussion
um i have to comment on all the other
comments before i get to my uh
i really enjoyed what uh convert was
saying and i think that resonates very
strongly with me that uh recon was
conrad was highlighting that um you know
the free energy principle and active
inferences and unsats it's a start to
think about something the difficult work
is actually trying to find what's the
right what uh called what you were
saying what's the lagrangian for the
things that we're interested in how is
it being
implemented i'm going to say something
before
i ask the question
because i also want to make sure that i
understand what you're saying
so let me say a couple of sentences and
then i want to formulate my question
so
um i understand active inference
is a theoretical and computational
prescription
[Music]
for normative behavior in complex
environment that is fundamentally based
on bayesian influence
and as stated by you
prime probability distributions are used
within the constraint of the free energy
principle to arrive at posterior
distribution that quantified
the behavior to be observed that is most
consistent with the underlying belief
about the nature of the environment
so that's my understanding
as i would say and so but as a as a so
now i'm putting my my psychiatry head up
you know um i'm into uh
i'm interested in alteration or
dysfunction of behavior
if i'm correct with my premise of what i
just stated and if you you can correct
me and i could be wrong and that's what
i want to but if i if that is sort of
the correct premise so alterations of
dysfunction of behavior can be conceived
in this framework in this anzacs
um as extending from
an altered and possibly inaccurate
belief about the state of the
environment
or
by a faulty integration of available
evidence
to form adaptive posterior distribution
um and so my question um
that i wanted to kind of just get your
input on
um
how might one arbitrate between those
two different um alternatives
um and um
and and maybe more
in the biology how might these different
differences be implemented but we
probably won't have time
to discuss this um
because i also actually think and now
i'm coming becoming sort of more real
practical um
um you know because
a and b
could mean different things for
remediation or intervention right
because one of the things that we want
to do if peop if people because i'm a
psychiatrist or animals if if you're an
animal person uh who behave in such a
way that we would agree
in in some form is non-adaptive we want
to help them to become
more adaptive but if the dysfunction is
based on fixed prior probabilities about
their environment or faulty
computation the the remediation might be
actually quite uh different
and therefore you know we need to find
almost ways of arbitrating between those
two alternatives and so i'd like to get
sort of your perspective on that and how
would you go about doing that
thank you thank you i'm sorry um yeah
well you know how how i do it i do it
like you're doing it
let's actually ask
a cheeky question um
so um the way i resolve this
mathematically now it's a really
interesting question but i i i sort of
deflate the question the problem is you
know is this broken inference um or just
bad prize yeah bad prize with
with with with great message passing
schemes or broken message schemes with
good prize
and that's a really interesting
distinction but practically i don't
think it's terribly um it's
it's
terribly meaningful from a practical
point of view um so i dismiss that with
something called the complete class
theorem and the complete class theorem
just says for any pair of observable
behavior and some loss function there
are some prior beliefs that render that
behavior based optimal so what that
allows me to do is say that everything
that's broken can be cast as a as a
an unusual prior so that this prior
is
so unusual that it looks as if it's a
faulty message passing system so i had a
prior belief about attention deployment
and precision and while i'm here just
open brackets of course
this is a lovely connection between
precision convergence and precision in
the sense of mark and deploying
attention you know
and indeed from uh martin your point of
view your deficits of attention and
deficits of consciousness are implicit
in deficit attention so precision here
getting the precision right these sort
of um inferences about the variability
or the um the width of probability
distributions in terms of the encoding
of uncertainty
say that i had bad prize about that what
would that look like well it would look
like i had an attention deficit disorder
that would look as if i had faulty
evidence accumulation and assimilation
that would look as if i basically had a
broken imprint scheme so what i do is i
i don't worry about it what i say is the
real job and then you come back to your
second i think key point um the real job
is to find out what part of this deeply
structured hierarchical generative model
that is a genetic model of dynamics um
is broken
sorry not it is broken is uh and that is
described by um
you know
by its
priors uh and formal prize in terms of
its structure what part is abnormal yes
broken in in this kind of person or this
disease relative to another another
disease that's i think the question
you're asking of course it is exactly
the practical question that conrad was
referring to and just to pick up on one
um you know your excellent summary of of
active imprints um
um
that is if you like an application the
free energy principle you're absolutely
it's just a prescription it's a
prescription as a method of waiving
things so just like hamilton's principle
of least action it's a method so you
give me a particular ball and a
particular sort of
cannon and i'll tell you the trajectory
but before you do that
there's nothing for me to do
so all the heavy lifting and all the
hard work because it's basically
finding the generative model
now under the assumption that you know
you can now apply the free energy
principle variational inference of an
inactive sort or active inference
then that provides a good account or
explanation of this person's behavior
then the job is just the normal
clinical neuroscience problem of finding
what part of this charity model is
different and by this part i mean the
particular prize and usually hyper
prized and they're usually um
as you will
you can't respond because it's my turn
to talk but what marty would like to say
they're the kind of prize and there are
these higher order prizes
whose biological substrates are probably
tied up with um neuromodulators and
synaptic excitability and all the
physiology that goes hand-in-hand with
that sort of fast
synchronous interactions and the like so
a very specific class of uh of part of
neurobiology that deals with with uh
modulators and particular kinds of
neuropharmacology
and this i think is a perfect example of
actually sort of saying what of the
universe of this deeply structured
genetic model that um you know is not
only um describing a person but in a
cultured context
what's remarkable about this prior
relative to this normal typical uh prior
and that's a really difficult game
obviously yeah
i actually had a second so so even
though this has already been a very uh
fascinating discussion for me i actually
had a second question because we were
asked to have two questions i do i want
to that's a little more edgy not edgy
for you but edgy maybe in in the sign of
times um which is the fact is and you
you actually have now expanded which is
very uh i i i just can't wait to see
what you're going to do
with the message message passing scheme
between active inference agents right
because now we're talking more than one
agent and you you gave the the nice
examples of the 20 questions
and how
one can develop a common
um
[Music]
framework to then
arrive at the correct solution
but of course again coming back to the
fact that i'm interested in when
behavior goes wrong
we live in a time
first of all let me just say that you
know even psychiatric disorders or
abnormal behavior individuals are not
islands they're embedded in
in in communities
and these communities interact heavily
and therefore doing the kind of message
passing
that you're talking about
but coming back to first principles you
know we live also in a time where it
seems like
that some agents together are very good
in message passing and other agents are
very good in
message passing and arriving at some
consensus but then there is
nucleations
that seem to be occurring and they seem
to be getting
more prominent and more severe
in in the current time
where there is very little message
passing
going between those nucleations and so
my question would be um how how would
you understand that as uh emerging
uh from uh sort of an active inference
principled agent that interacts with
other active inference
um principled agents
yeah that's a great question and i
suspect it probably will probably just
use that question when we come back to
sort of round and summarize one of the
ways forward
so
the way that i would do that is
basically by numerical analysis and i
would write down a little world and see
what emerges
when each
member of a population or ensemble
you know is described or its behavior is
prescribed by uh by active inference
and what i would imagine would happen is
this dialectic between trying to make
your world as predictable predictable
and at least surprising as possible um
whilst at the same time trying to share
your genetic model with as many
artifacts like you that are generating
the things you're trying to predict will
be resolved by this nucleation and this
sort of blanket building um
isolationism if you like a sort of
partial isolationism um that
characterizes so many aspects of our
sort of
political and geo and
familial cultures and structures that
there is again a scale invariance that
does entail um
sort of a markov blanketing or
blanketing or segregation or partial
segregation that fulfills that within
your blanket within your family within
your
ethnic or political or religious um you
know
culture
there is a shared narrative and
everything is nice and predictable um
and that that
that sort of encapsulation is
underwritten by something we're
referring to before which is this
bayes optimality in terms of bi-sampling
you know if i act to realize the kind of
world i think i'm
built to uh self-evidence in then i'm
going to construct into the extent that
i'm going to be successful in so doing
collectively then those boundaries will
um will will be maintained the question
now is of course you know what is the
scale the structure the number of these
of these communities that are emerging
properties very much in the spirit of
turing pattern formation that you know
we're talking about uh i was talking
before about alan turing i mean this is
exactly the kind of segregation reaction
diffusion-like phenomena um
he wanted to understand and i would
imagine that the same
techniques will be used uh a century
later and by which i mean he started off
by basically doing by hand excel
spreadsheets and looking at sort of
local exchanges to look at your
self-organization and
pattern formation we would do it in
computers but actually probably just
about the same speed because we'll be
actually modeling active inference
agents that actually are modeling
everybody else in their eco niche
and who knows what will happen but
hopefully for a sufficient number of
scale invariant
aspects to this
procedure you'll see what tends to
happen in your own brain that you
actually get functional specialization
in the context of integration um so you
get distributed processing but there is
segregation of function um and you know
you can chase that right down to the
structure of a neuron or right up to the
structure of your body there are
symmetries but there's also
specialization so i imagine that there
will be a similar kind of
structures emerging that will be
describable in terms of
the dependency kind of causality through
markov blankets
that one could be looking for
in silico
thanks uh carl in the interest of time
you're right what you just said is
essentially the overall round table but
in the interest of time i would like
that we
uh intro we get the commentary of the la
of the last two presenters and you
integrate your reply into we will start
our round table with you
uh
cal for the last so if it's okay ally
and uh
daniel will be uh presenting their
commentary and then we'll start the the
round table uh with you and your answer
to those two at the same time of the
general question how do we go for this
real procedure called results sound back
to you to introduce alain
it's my pleasure to introduce dr elaine
dagger who is associate professor at the
montreal neurologic institute and mcgill
university a neurologist specializing in
movement disorders and functional brain
imaging and little known
a fantasy american football
aficionado you so thank you uh carl for
a really inspiring talk and
uh i i have two related questions or
comments one has to do with what you
refer as your day job uh functional
neuroimaging
we've been able to measure blood flow in
the brain for a few decades now and in
the early days we just asked questions
like what does what
but i think the more interesting
prospect is to try to measure
information in the brain
and specifically to ask how is
information processed in the brain
and one way
that you have promoted is to try to
quantify cognitive processes and then
relate them to brain activity and i
wonder what you think the prospects are
for for this area
and specifically i'd like to ask you
about dopamine which encodes information
in multiple ways
and i'd like to specifically ask you
about tonic dopamine
because
it seems to be related to motivation
into the willingness to act in the world
patients with low dopamine low tonic
dopamine so that's the dopamine that
basically bathes neurons
these patients experience apathy
despite the fact that they still enjoy
life and they still have the ability to
experience pleasure they're not willing
to act
and conversely when we increase their
tonic dopamine with medications we can
trigger states of maladaptive action
such as pathological gambling and
compulsive sexuality
and i was trying to think where tonic
dopamine fits in the free energy
principle and i was wondering whether it
could
encode expected information
and that that alone could explain uh its
its effects on apathy and motivation
quite interesting uh do you have another
question elaine before i introduce that
no that that's the that's okay
very good uh in let's shift to uh
dandelski
who
was wondering why that we had invited
him on the panel and it was very very
carefully
uh selected for
donnie's working from the genes to
society is working on issue of aging
life-course socio-economic status that
uh are so important if we are to create
this next generation
science of real-world behavior in real
world context in a more adaptive manner
so dan is assistant professor of
epidemiology at columbia university uh
melbourne school of public health and uh
also um at the robert butler uh columbia
aging center so down what i don't i let
you to all the space we can get go ahead
then
well thank you so much um for having me
for the invitation uh it was a
fascinating talk uh and and equally
fascinating questions from the panelists
uh i've learned a great deal um
and in fact the questions that i
initially wrote down to pose to carl uh
which were about
how
this model
speaks to the development of individual
differences and in particular uh how
that happens across uh time scales of
human development um
across the lifespan have been partly
answered in in the responses in
particular to randy regarding time um
and to martin uh regarding uh the
genesis of individual differences so in
in
service of transitioning us toward that
overall panel let me pose the more
general question to carl from the public
health perspective since i'm here from
the department of epidemiology and i
know you've um uh
been thinking uh about public health and
epidemiology in the context of your
models uh recently um
how should
the free energy principle inform the
kinds of strategies
that
we are developing to shape
public behavior
private behavior in service of of
cultivating health for individuals
across their lives and that's a
that's a um you know maybe the the
opposite end of the spectrum from alan's
question which is you know very
specifically about a particular
mechanism that you've thought about and
i guess i'm asking
more generally
not what does this say to you know sort
of public health in general but what are
applications that you might envision
of the free energy principle that could
guide us toward
a more precise approach to public health
and social policy um
than where we stand today um and perhaps
you know we can have some further
interaction in the subsequent q a
thank you very much don
and i would like to make sure that all
the panelists are having their video on
we have uh 12 more minutes in those 12
more minutes we
will have a cal
addressing those first two
uh
those first two uh uh last two
commentaries but within the broader
perspective call of your word of wisdom
how can we as a
worldwide community move toward this
next generation precision convergence
uh convergence science so carl has two
or three minutes and each of you will
have one minute after
and then sean and me will be uh
concluding go ahead calm
thank you very much
your question and elaine's question are
actually i think of of the same milk and
like really important and also speak to
uh what we were discussing with martin
which is you know you've got um
a principle a recipe how are you going
to make it
work in a useful way in different scales
um so you know the in answer to to
daniel's question um one can um
drill down on
um
the
the the
the individual
on the single person
in terms of their neurology and their
psychology um as an individual and try
to understand the functional
architectures and the physiology of the
belief updating and the um
the
message passing neural message passing
very much along the lines that we're
discussing with mark and with martin so
this basically would be uh understanding
neurology psychiatry and indeed behavior
as
aberrant belief updating from the point
of view of active influence but because
you've got this process theory
underneath the hood that that grounds
into neurobiology you've also now got a
way of articulating
psychopathology
in terms of pathophysiology things that
are you know
that are aberrant and highly unlikely in
terms of the physiology and the dynamics
and the structure the neuroanatomy of a
particular brain so that you know you
know
that is if you like you're already an
active research part of say
computational psychiatry and
computational uh neuropsychology you
just build things in silico you see you
make sure you optimize them so they
behave exactly like your patient you do
a bit of precision medicine just by
nuancing and adjusting and optimizing
the price of this
digital twin if you like um that
complies with the the method of the free
energy principle
then i think you have to move up to the
next level which we already talked about
which is the um
the exchange between agents and issues
of um
data foraging not data so
i meant sort of information foraging
epistemic trust static interactions
therapeutic engagement uh martin if you
had time would speak to this you know
how can you use these principles to
predict the kind of prior beliefs that
people will have will
commit to
um that
ensures a therapeutic engagement with
the doctor say or with the public health
service these are really important
issues um to understand the mechanics of
the belief updating in terms of
interpersonal inference may be really
important in just
supplying public health care uh let
alone you know what that care the
content of that care and then at the
next level we're talking about
epidemiological modelling um but we
haven't done that yet in the sense that
when we model viruses
um
and model people the vectors of those
viruses the people are just like points
like this the physics spherical cow that
they don't insert in in
themselves have any um
uh intentions or prior beliefs that's an
outstanding issue and i repeat i think
that's where we're going to end up
i won't finish that because i want to
just comment alan's that's a great idea
i haven't thought about that
sorry dopamine may well be the encoding
of the expected information gain of the
you know the epistemic value of
that's really very interesting i think
it's entirely licensed because um
speaking to the exchange with martin um
what we're talking about here is prior
beliefs about the precision or the
confidence or the certainty with which
you sub personally your brain holds
certain beliefs
that means for every probability
distribution every probabilistic
representation in the brain there is a
precision that may or may not be encoded
implicitly or explicitly with a
neurotransmitter so that certainly
speaks to a plurality
of things that things like dopamine
might encode we certainly know something
to do with plans and action but beyond
that i think that the hypothesis it
could be expected information gain is
exactly the same kind of hypothesis that
you would then use simulations to test
by you know
playing off expected
cost for example against expected
information gain factorially and seeing
which was the best account for dopamine
in this region as opposed to dopamine
responses in that region that's a
excellent idea but would be part of this
basically
building a brain in silico optimizing it
using the principles we've been talking
about to you know to drill down uh you
know in a precision medicine
kind of fashion um which would be one
end of the scale from a public health
perspective the other end of the scale
being where i'm going to finish which is
the agenda that days
do you uh you want to go with your one
minute commentary on the where we go
from here well in a sense i i the last
the last 30 seconds was was meant to be
you know i think we've identified you
know what where the challenges are and
it's basically something which
everybody's spoken to some level from
conrad how you have the complexity of it
all from randy you know how do you get
the multiple time skills from you know
daniel how do you how do you get this to
the level of public health it's all
about basically
um
self-organization of sentient artifacts
at different scales so it is exactly
collective agency so that's the big
challenge uh the last thing i'd like to
say
is i i hope i get the uh the phd that'll
be quite clear oh you do absolutely
you get many post doc so let's let's
have this 30 second to one minute
commentary for
each of you you can you can
on vote
other phd but most importantly i want to
hear from you where do we go as a
capacity building worldwide community in
the next six months of the year uh mark
yes i will follow the same order than we
had in the panel mark
so alan turing keeps coming up in the
conversation today and i don't think
that's an accident turing's world view
included the theory of computation and i
don't mean digital computers in your
laptop i mean the the theory of
information dynamics as a unifying
theory of everything and it permeated
all of his scholarship and i i you know
i don't want to talk my own book here
but but i think the theory of
computation offers fertile
basic ground just like set theory did a
couple of centuries ago for mathematics
to create a common language and a common
set of models
thank you
i think building this the underlying
theory for machine learning is very very
important and more broadly for
neuroscience which means if we're in
these normative spaces oftentimes our
algorithms do a lot of arbitrary things
and i think there's a lot of wonderful
recent developments in the area where
you can then
prove that say you will generalize for a
certain set of phenomena like pac-bay
i'm thinking of ideas like pack bass
and and and i
i think not like and they interface with
theories of how the world was now they
they depend on all these
pieces that we come in
that we put in and i think there will
there's there's a lot of development
that we need to make these ideas be
concrete thank you
lauren
um
i mean what i take away from this is
that um
there is a lot of work to be done and
thinking about how to
build the generative models that we need
to answer some of these questions
i think as conrad posted some of the
examples of the application of free
energy in the domain of cobit modeling
we've done something similar um using
merging agent-based models with some
sort of sir models and that's also a
generative model just a question of the
objective functions i think this is a
domain that
kind of extends beyond just thinking
about the the tool itself but thinking
about the application and where the
application can take us and that's i
think been a constant theme
um so it's not just so much thinking
only about free energy per se but also
you know what do we want what do we want
to understand and can we use the free
energy to to
engender new understanding of these
problems
thank you martin
kevin very brief i want to thank carl
for challenging all of us
to think harder about
you know how behavior emerges and how it
breaks down
again i'm excited to see what
multi-agent active inference uh
will look like and what
you know what patterns emerge and how we
can potentially use the insights
to make the la the world a better place
thank you alain
okay thank you well i think that the
challenge is to see uh what is a
vulnerable brain at least in medicine
and and
understand how genes and environment
conspire to create a vulnerable brain
and to understand that vulnerable at a
at a computational level so that's the
interesting challenge of the next
few years
done
i mean i think i would just echo alan i
think i think
i was inspired by mark's initial
comments about the idea of information
as a fundamental element in the universe
and genetics as an encoding of that
information and so the way in which um
that information interacts with the
inner information of our experience to
produce variation and behavior is
is the is the frontier um and and i i
should also just say i'm grateful that
lauren has returned and so uh
oh boy
um well
yeah so i
um
i mean carl's work is already bringing
together many approaches and i think
this is
particularly useful for
many questions especially ones that are
kind of on the edge of
discovery and in some sense the edge of
science so where do we go from here i
think we can um
kind of capitalize on this and do more
of this having more discussions asking
more questions and
more attempts to answer them so
thank you
thank you shifting to you
uh in fact lorenzon uh shifting to use
on almost use the expression you are
using what we are doing is brings
bridging the edge of science i will let
you speak for yourself or your
commentary but also introduce our next
precision convergence uh that is in fact
a very nice buildup
to what we were having uh today go ahead
sean
yeah and i gotta do it quick because i
have to go meet my dean uh but thank you
for the wonderful talk carl and thank
you all the panelists for a
mind-expanding conversation i feel like
uh
uh you know you're talking lagrangians
message passing free energy i feel like
i'm in a quantum chemistry talk again
which is my background but uh it's it's
it was really uh
interesting and stimulating talk in our
next presentation will be i believe on
may 24th
is putting
the poster in the chat thing
from mit we'll be talking about uh both
how
basically how neural uh neuroinformatics
is facilitated by infrastructure
development he is the lead on an
infrastructure project called dandy
which is a microservices architecture
for bringing together neuroscience
pipelines and data so
a very different talk but still
interesting nonetheless but thank you
again carl for what a very wonderful
presentation
yes indeed thanks to
carl uh
we very very much appreciate uh you
placing this in your busy schedule and
each of you on the panel and those in
the audience also uh we all know what
two hours mean and we appreciate very
much
uh not only the time but the brain
investment in the last two
hours uh is indeed building this
capacity for
precision convergence which is this edge
of science connecting all of the above
for
real-world transformation in as
real-time as possible thank you everyone
we will end here
uh and we hope to have you on the next
one but most importantly
um it is it is uh
a community we are building so we will
be getting in touch in that in diverse
manner thanks to all of you bye-bye
you